<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Queene. The Queenes Maiesty vnderstanding of the common wandring abroad of a great multitude of her people, whereof the most part pretend, that they haue serued in the warres of late on the other side of the seas  ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1591-11-05</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115449</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 565:71)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Queene. The Queenes Maiesty vnderstanding of the common wandring abroad of a great multitude of her people, whereof the most part pretend, that they haue serued in the warres of late on the other side of the seas  ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1591-11-05</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Against vagrant soldiers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogues and vagabonds --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soldiers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15889:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Queene.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queenes Maieſty vnderſtanding of the common wandring abroad of a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of her people, whereof the moſt part pretend, that they haue ſerued in the warres of late on the other ſide of the Seas, though in trueth it is knowen, that very mante of them, either haue not ſerued at all, or haue bene licenced to depart from the places of their ſeruice, as they ought to haue beene, but haue runne away from their ſeruice, and therefore they are fuſtly to be puniſhed, and not to be relieued: ſome others are ſuch as haue indeede ſerued, and fallen into ſickenſſe, and therefore lienced to departe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their Countries, from whence they were leuied, and doe deſerue reliefe, To the intent all her Maieſties Officers of Iuſtice in euery place, where theſe ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall reſort, may knowe, what her Maieſties moſt gracio pleaſure is, for the vſage of the ſaide perſons, both to puniſh the offendours, and to relieue the ſiche ſouldiours, and ſuch as haue truely ſerued, and are licenced to departe to their Countryes: She commaundeth that ſuch diſcretion be vſed berwixt the vnlawfull vagarant perſons, and the ſouldiours now lawfully diſmiſſed from their ſeruices, that all ſuch vagarant perſons, as neyther haue beene brought to ſickeneſſe nor lameneſſe by the ſaide late ſeruice, and that ſhall not be able to ſhe we ſufficient paſport for their diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall be taken and apprehended, whereſoeuer they may be found, as perſons vagabonds, and ſo to be puniſhed. And if any of them ſhall alleadge, that they haue bene in her Maieſties pay on the other ſide the Seas, and cannot ſhe we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient paſport from the Lord Generall, or ſome of the principall Officers of the armie, then to be taken and committed to priſon, and to be indited as felons, and to ſuffer for the ſame, as ſouldiours being in her Maieſties pay, that haue runne away, and left the ſeruice traiterouſly. And for the reſt that haue ſerued as ſouldiours, and can ſhe we thier law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſports, they ought to be relieued by ſome charitable meanes, to conduct them into their Countrey, with commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of publique Letters from the Iuſtices of the Peace where they ſhall be found, to all other Miniſters both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, both to graunt them reaſonable reliefe and ayde for their paſſage, and to bee particularly relieued by the Pariſhes or Hundreds, from whence they were leuied during the time of their infirmities and ſickeneſſe, as in conſcience they ought, and ſo to be placed with their former Maſters, as by her Maieſties late directions to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hath bene ordered and appoynted: And neuertheleſſe, with ſpeciall paynes to be added to the ſame Letters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of Paſports, that if they ſhall bee found to wander abroad out of the ordinary wayes mentioned in their Paſports, that then, they are to be puniſhed as vagabonds.</p>
            <p>And her Maieſtie letteth it to be knowen, that order is giuen by her, that her Treaſorer of warres hath and ſhal make payment (in euery Port where any ſuch ſhall arriue comming with lawfull Paſport) of ſuch ſummes of money, as ſhall be conuentient to conduct them to the places from which they were leuied. And that all Officers of Ports ſhall be allowed by the ſayd Treaſorer any ſuch ſummes of money, as by them ſhall be payde to any ſuch lawfull ſouldiers. And furthermore, for the repreſſing of the great number of mightie &amp; hable vagarant perſons now wandring abroad vnder pretence of begging as ſouldiers, although in deed they are known to commit open robberies vpon her Maieſties poore ſubiects and trauaillers by the way: Her Maieſtie ſtraightly chargeth all her Lieutenantes of euery Countie within the Realme (hauing ſufficient warrant by their Commiſſion to execute Martiall Law vpon ſuch offenders againſt the publike peace and ſtate of the Realme) to appoynt ſome ſpeciall perſons within their iuriſdictions to trauell within the Counties as Prouſt-Marſhals, and to giue directions to the Iuſtices of the Peace to aſſiſt the Prouoff-Marſhall, for the apprehenſion of all ſuch notable offenders, and to commit them to priſon, and thereupon to be executed, as by the Lawes of the Realme they ſhall deſerue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen our Mannor of Richmond, <date>the fift day of Nouember and in the three and thirtieth yeere of our raigne.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by the Deputies of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
